Guide to the Israel Kugler Papers TAM.315
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Israel Kugler Papers
1951-2007
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Kugler, Israel, 1917-2007
TAM.315
1.5 Linear Feet 1 record carton and 2 manuscript boxes
Israel Kugler (1917-2007) was born in Brooklyn and a graduate of City College (1938). He earned a Ph.D. from New York University in sociology and taught for many years at New York Community College. He was a member of the Young People's Socialist League and later of the Socialist Party. As a founding member and president of the United Federation of College Teachers (UFCT) and a founding member and officer of the Professional Staff Congress (PSC), he was a key figure in faculty/staff unionism at the City University of New York (CUNY). A vocal advocate of civil rights, he was involved in the AFT's national adoption of a resolution revoking the charters of segregated locals in 1955. He led the historic 1966-1967 faculty strike at St. John's University. Raised in the traditions of immigrant Jewish socialism, he was a life-long devotee of Yiddish culture and served as national president of the Workmen's Circle, board member of the Jewish Labor Committee and president of the Three Arrows Cooperative Society. The collection consists mainly of his writings and presentations in various fields of interest, and also includes biographical material and subject files on his political and labor affiliations and activities.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives by Israel Kugler in 2004. Obituaries were added after Kugler's death in 2007. Photographs and a VHS tape separated from the collection during initial processing were discovered in the repository in 2014 and added to the collection as Box 2. The accession numbers related to this gift are 2004.009, NPA.2005.178, and 2014.122.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Organized into 1 series:
Missing Title
I, General Files, 1951-2007.
Historical/Biographical Note
Israel Kugler was a noted advocate for and leader of academic unionism, professor of sociology, labor arbitrator, democratic socialist activist and devotee of Yiddish culture. Born in Brooklyn, New York, he received his bachelor's degree from City College in 1938. He married Helen Barkan in 1941 and they were to have two sons, Daniel and Philip. After serving in the Navy during World War II, he earned his M.A. and Ph.D. in sociology from New York University in 1954, writing a dissertation on the relationship between the mid-nineteenth century women's suffrage movement and the National Labor Union. In 1947 he was appointed a faculty member in social science at New York City Community College (now New York City College of Technology), where he taught until 1980.
Kugler was a key figure in the United Federation of College Teachers (UFCT), which originated as a section of the Teachers Guild and later the United Federation of Teachers and became Local 1460 of the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). The UFCT represented faculty and professional staff in both public and private institutions of higher education. Kugler had served as vice-president of the Guild/UFT section from 1954 and became president of the UFCT in 1963. Within a few years Kugler had led successful organizing organizing campaigns at Fashion Institute of technology, Long Island University, Pratt Institute and several other campuses.
During the mid-1950s, Kugler led a group which advocated that the AFT adopt a resolution which would suspend the charters of segregated locals. This resolution was adopted by the AFT in 1955.
In the fall of 1965, 31 faculty members at St. John's University in Queens (then one of the largest Catholic universities in the world) were notified of their dismissal or contract termination as of the end of the academic year, without any charges, hearings or other form of due process. Kugler led a faculty strike which began in January of 1966, and included not only demands related to the dismissed members, but also issues of salary and benefits. It was the first strike in the United States by the faculty of a four-year institution of higher education. The strike lasted until June 1967, when St. John's agreed to arbitration. Although the St. John's strike did not result in reinstatement of the faculty or official recognition of the union, it did establish the AFT as a leader in the unionization of faculty and staff in higher education.
In 1972 Kugler, along with Belle Zeller, president of the UFCT's long-time rival, the Legislative Conference, finally concluded the hard-won merger of the two organizations into the Professional Staff Congress (PSC), a unified representative body (and bargaining agent) for faculty and technical staff at the City University of New York. He served as the Deputy President of the PSC from 1972 until 1973.
Beginning in 1977, Kugler frequently served as a labor arbitrator; he was a panelist with the American Arbitration Association, the New York State Mediation Board and the National Mediation Board, among others. He also served as president of The Workmen's Circle, a national Jewish fraternal organization, from 1980 until 1984.
He was affiliated with many organizations, including the Three Arrows Cooperative Society, the League for Industrial Democracy, the Jewish Labor Committee, the Industrial Relations Research Association, Social Democrats, USA and the Forward Association. In June 1997 the New York City Technical College and the City University granted him an honorary doctorate in Humane Letters.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
IK interview in Jewish Labor Committee Oral History Collection. (OH 027)
IK interview in New Yorkers at Work Oral History Collection. (OH 001)
Three Arrows Cooperative Society Records. (TAM 250)
Professional Staff Congress/City College of New York Records. (WAG 009)
Jewish Labor Committee Records (WAG 025 001, WAG 025 002, WAG 025 003)
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists largely of lectures and writings which illustrate Kugler's interest in a wide variety of subjects ranging from educational theory and faculty unionism to women's rights, New York labor history, Yiddish culture and Israeli politics. The writings include an unpublished autobiographical manuscript entitled, "One Eye on the Stars". Also included are subject files for organizations with which Kugler was affiliated, as well as travel journals and itineraries from his extensive travels throughout Europe, South America, Asia, the Middle East, and the USSR. Of special note are files on the Association of Jewish Book Publishers' 1981 Book Fair in Moscow and on the United Federation of College Teachers and the Professional Staff Congress.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Separated Material
A file of photographs was separated to the Non-Print Department of the Tamiment Library.
New York (N.Y.).; Universities and colleges |x Employees |x Labor unions |z United States.; Correspondence.; Autobiographies.; College teachers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Lectures.; Journals (periodicals); Manuscripts; Professional Staff Congress/City University of New York; United Federation of College Teachers; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring; Kugler, Israel, 1917-2007; Jewish Labor Committee (U.S.); American Federation of Teachers; Forward Association
- Series I: General Files, 1951-2007.
  - American Federation of Teachers: "Fighting for the Profession: A History of AFT Higher Education" (pamphlet), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arbitration: Cases and Awards, 1975, 1977, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Association of Jewish Book Publishers Third Annual Moscow Book Fair: Catalogs, Notes, Clippings, 1981-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Information, undated, 1980, 2005-2007 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Brazil: Travel Itinerary and Information, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clippings (Yiddish, re: IK), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Forward Association, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Glotzer, Albert: Commemoration: Program and Tributes, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Greenwood Press: Publishing Aids, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Israel: History (clippings), 1979, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Israel Kugler Testimonial Luncheon (Retirement), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jewish Labor Committee: Delegation to the Federal Republic of Germany, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Johnpoll, Bernard K: "The Yiddish Press in the United States", undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Lectures: "The 50th Anniversary of the State of Israel", [1998] (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lectures: "The 52nd Anniversary of the State of Israel", [2000] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lectures: "Ellis Island and the Jewish Immigration", undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Lectures: "Israel Kugler Testimonial Luncheon", 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lectures: "John Commerford Labor Education Award to Sol Stetin", undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lectures: "On the Hundredth Anniversary of the Yiddish Forverts", undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lectures: "The American Yiddish Theater: Origins and History", undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lectures: "The Workmen's Circle and the American Jewish Labor Movement", undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Letters to the Editor: Jewish Daily Forward, 1991-2000 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Letters to the Editor: Other Periodicals, 1983-2002 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Libo, Kenneth: "Education of a Socialist" (Kugler interview, Jewish Daily Forward), Aug 24, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Lipsky, Seth: "Abraham Cahan, The Forward, and Me" ( Commentary), Jun 1997 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Marsh, Alice: Commemoration: Program, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mlotek, Yosl: Commemoration: Program, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - New York City Technical College: Doctor of Humane Letters Honorary Degree Citation (program), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - North American Federation of Secular Humanistic Jews, 1985, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Perry, Michael S: Labor Rights in the Jewish Tradition(publ. Jewish Labor Committee), undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Retirement: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Social Democrats, USA, 1987-1993 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Three Arrows Cooperative Society, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Travel Journal: Asia (Indonesia, Bali, Bangkok, Japan, Taiwan), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Travel Journal: Brazil, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - United Federation of College Teachers and Professional Staff Congress: History, 1965-1966, 1980-1982, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Workmen's Circle: Delegation to Israel in Cooperation with the Moshe Sharrett Institute, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Workmen's Circle: "Where We Stand" (Resolutions Adopted by Conventions), 1998, 2000, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Writings: "1492--The Expulsion of the Jews from Spain--Thereafter" (typescript and research material), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Writings: "250,000 Children of Our Fathers" ( Midstream), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Writings: "A Life in the Workmen's Circle: Reminiscence and Reflection" ( Labor's Heritage), Oct 1991 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Writings: "A Missed Opportunity: Jews and Blacks" ( Midstream), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Writings: "Al Shanker--Colleague and Comrade" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Writings: "Alice Marsh" (typescript), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Writings: "Anemia in Academe" ( Dissent), 1986 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Writings: "Arbeter Ring Schul – As I Remember It" ( The Call), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Writings: "Arguing With 'Arguing the World'" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Writings: "Campus Unrest: Some Elements of Analysis" ( The Call), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Writings: "For Jews--The Secular Humanistic Alternative" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Writings: From Ladies to Women: The Organized Struggle for Woman's Rights in the Reconstruction Era(reviews), 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Writings: "Irving Howe--1921-1993: A Reminiscence and Appreciation" (typescript) (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Writings: "Jewish Day School: The Values at Stake" ( The Call), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Writings: "Killers of the Dream" (typescript), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Writings: "Labor Rights" (Draft Resolution for Workmen's Circle), 2004 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Writings: "Ladies into Women: Organizing for Rights in America", undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Writings: "Making College Teaching and Learning Possible" ( Concord), 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Writings: "On Racism and Freedom of Speech" (Leonard Jeffries Case; Letter to the Jewish Daily Forward), Jan 25, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Writings: "On Sandra Feldman" (typescript), 2005 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Writings: "One Eye on the Stars" (unpublished autobiographical manuscript), Foreword, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Writings: "One Eye on the Stars," Chapters I-V, undated (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Writings: "One Eye on the Stars," Chapters VI-VIII, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Writings: "Our Philosophy" ( Horizons of Culture and Life– Workmen's Circle Newsletter), 1991 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Writings: "Our Semi-Centennial: Meanderings of a Participant-Observer" ( Queens-View News), 2000 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Writings: Review of Harry Van Arsdale, Jr.--Labor's Champion(typescript), 2002 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Writings: Review of Look for the Union Label: A History of the International Ladies Garment Workers Union( Labor History), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Writings: "Secular Humanistic Judaism--A Jewish Alternative" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Writings: Sociological Survey of Extra-Curricular Activities (State University of New York), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Writings: "Status, Power, and Educational Freedom" ( Journal of Educational Sociology), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Writings: "The Jewish Daily Forward: A Vision through a Child's Prism" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Writings: "The Laggard in Academe" ( Concord), 1966 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Writings: "The 1966 Strike at St. John's University: A Memoir" ( Labor's Heritage), 1997 (Box 1, Folder 70a)
  - Writings: "The Public Welfare Department: A Community Resource in Social Education" ( The Social Studies), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Writings: "The Student-Volunteer Social Worker" ( Journal of Higher Education), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Writings: "The Technical Institute and General Education" ( Junior College Journal), 1951 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Writings: "The Trade Union Career of Susan B. Anthony" ( Labor History), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Writings: "The Union Speaks for Itself" ( Educational Record), 1968 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Writings: "The Warsaw Ghetto Uprising: An Anniversary" ( Midstream), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Writings: "The Workmen's Circle – 90 Years Young" ( Midstream), 1993 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Writings: "The Workmen's Circle and the Forward" ( The Forward), 1980 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Writings: Unionism: "A New Instrument for Faculty Governance" ( ISR Journal), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Writings: "Who Runs the Modern College" (unpublished manuscript) Chapters I-VIII, undated (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Writings: "Women in Jewish Life" (typescript), undated (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Writings: "Women's Rights Movement and National Labor Union" (Dissertation Outline), undated (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Yeshiva University: National Labor Relations Board and Supreme Court Decisions (Correspondence and Clippings), 1989 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Photographs (mostly United Federation of Teachers) and Unlabeled VHS Tape, undated (Box 2)
  - VHS tapes, 1997-1999 (Box 3)